Finding Aid for Stanford R. Ovshinsky papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stanford R. Ovshinsky papers
1922-2012
1950-2012
Ovshinsky, Stanford R.
97.4 linear feet in 108 boxes
2014092 Aa 2
Collection documents the personal and professional life of Stanford R. Ovshinsky, Michigan inventor and pioneer in the field of amorphous materials; his work emphasized photovoltaics and batteries, among other areas. Includes correspondence, business files, technical publications and presentations, and related records documenting Ovshinsky's life, activities, accomplishments, and interests.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was donated in five installments by Rosa Ovshinsky (donor no. 10903 ), Harvey Ovshinsky (donor no. 10907 ), and Elihu Upham (donor no. 10906, in March-May, 2013.
The collection is open without restriction
Stanford ("Stan") Robert Ovshinsky was born November 24, 1922 in Akron, Ohio, to Benjamin and Bertha (Munitz) Ovshinsky, immigrants from Lithuania and Poland. He had two siblings, Herbert ("Herb") and Myrtle ("Mashie"), who was later known as Sandra. Ovshinsky married three times. On August 9, 1942, he was united in marriage with childhood friend Norma Rifkin; the relationship ended in divorce in 1959. To this union were born three sons, Benjamin, Harvey, and Dale. Ovshinsky subsequently wed Dr. Iris L. Dibner (née Miroy) in Toledo, Ohio, on March 30, 1962. Iris--an accomplished scientist with degrees in zoology, biology, and biochemistry--brought to their relationship two children of her own, Robin and Steven. Stan and Iris Ovshinsky worked successfully together for the long and happy duration of their marriage, crediting their combined advances in science to their loving relationship. Iris Ovshinsky's unexpected death in August 2006 devastated Ovshinsky. In late 2007, he married Dr. Rosa Young, whom he had known for more than twenty years through her work with Energy Conversion Devices. Stanford R. Ovshinsky passed away on October 17, 2012 at his home in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, leaving behind a wife, three children, four stepchildren, and several grandchildren.
Ovshinsky began his working life at Tann Corporation in the Congress Controls Division and served as Vice President of Cytrol Corporation before turning his attention to other areas of study. At the dawn of his career, Ovshinsky's lack of college credentials and the radical nature of his theories in the field of amorphous materials hindered the acceptance of his ideas by the scientific community, but his persistent dedication to his research eventually bore fruit. In 1968, Ovshinsky announced that he had discovered what was subsequently dubbed the Ovshinsky Effect, a phenomenon concerning the transformation of a nonconductive glassy thin film to a semiconductor with the application of a certain minimum voltage. This discovery, repeatedly corroborated by other researchers after Ovshinsky's announcement, marked a turning point in his life as a scientist.
By the 1970s, Ovshisky's writings on the subject of amorphous materials and memory had become cornerstones of an expanding, promising field and made his name a common one in scientific circles. Invitations to speak at technical conferences and at university commencements, where he was awarded a number of honorary degrees, took Stan and Iris Ovshinsky around the world and brought them into contact with many preeminent scientists. Over the course of his career, Ovshinsky earned his own remarkable place in the ranks of accomplishment, obtaining over 400 U.S. patents and penning more than 300 publications. He actively participated in research and continued to write technical articles, many of which he presented publicly, into his late eighties. The astonishing breadth and innovation of this work led prominent British newspaper The Economist to propose that Ovshinsky be considered "the Edison of our age."
A driven entrepreneur, Ovshinsky established numerous companies during his working life, building partnerships with a variety of national and international corporations. He started his first enterprise, Stanford Roberts Machine Company, around 1948. From this business was born one of Ovshinsky's first inventions, the Benjamin Center Drive lathe. Ovshinsky paid tribute his late father by naming the highly flexible, multipurpose machine in his honor. When the United States entered the Korean War in 1950, this lathe became a crucial and profitable tool in the production of massive amounts of shells for the American armed forces. Shortly before the beginning of the war, however, Ovshinsky sold both the Benjamin Center Drive and his business to the New Britain Machine Company, which was incorporated into Northrup Grumman after a series of acquisitions. In 1951, he accepted a new position with Hupp Motor Company as Director of Research and moved to the Detroit area, where he would reside for the rest of his life. At Hupp, Ovshinsky worked extensively in the development of improved power steering systems. On his own initiative, he also began studying the brain and principles of neurophysiology. This new interest prompted Ovshinsky and his brother Herb to found a business of their own, General Automation, where they created the Ovitron, a mechanical model of a nerve cell that functioned as a hybrid solid state/liquid state switching device. Stan and Herb Ovshinsky patented and publicized the machine, a pioneering example of nanostructures, in 1959. Around this time, General Automation was renamed Ovitron Corporation in honor of its groundbreaking invention.
Ovshinsky's entrepreneurship reached new heights in 1960, when he established Energy Conversion Laboratory with his future wife Iris. In 1964, the company changed its name to Energy Conversion Devices, Inc. (ECD). ECD underwent tremendous expansion over the subsequent decades, creating numerous subsidiary companies and forging business connections around the globe, including partnerships with General Motors, Chevron, and Texaco. Seeking to solve critical social and environmental problems through cutting-edge research, the company focused primarily on energy generation, energy storage, and information technology. ECD applied new knowledge and techniques of amorphous materials to improve solar energy collection and use, nickel-metal hydride batteries (prominently used in hybrid cars), imaging film and display, and a host of other technologies. Over the years, the company and its subsidiaries attracted many brilliant people as employees, board members, consultants, and investors. Robert C. Stempel, formerly CEO of and automotive engineer with General Motors, joined Energy Conversion Devices as an advisor and quickly became its chairman, a position he held for 12 years. Hellmut Fritzsche, another prominent scientist and long-time researcher at the University of Chicago, became an ECD board member in 1969 and later served as vice president until his resignation in 2003. Fritzsche also worked with two of the company's subsidiaries, joining United Solar Systems as a member of their Board of Directors and Ovonic Battery Company as Chief Operating Officer. Other prominent scientists involved with ECD included David Adler, a celebrated physicist at Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and Sir Nevill Mott, a distinguished British scientist and Nobel Prize winner in physics. While working at ECD, Ovshinsky also founded the Institute for Amorphous Studies (IAS), bringing together many of the scientists working in the field of amorphous materials and hosting lectures offered by members of the institute. Among the speakers who presented at IAS were at least five Nobel Laureates, a contributor to the Manhattan Project, and a pantheon of prominent academics at some of the world's top universities, colleges, and research organizations.
In 2007, following company disputes, Ovshinsky retired from ECD and began another enterprise, Ovshinsky Innovation LLC, with fellow scientist Rosa Young; he and Rosa married later that year. Ovshinsky led this company until his death from cancer in 2012, just one month shy of his 90th birthday. Shortly before Ovshinsky passed away, Energy Conversion Devices filed for bankruptcy, announced plans to dissolve, and liquidated its remaining assets.
This collection is divided into eight series: Personal; Correspondence; Research and Subject Files; Publications; Business Administration; Talks and Recognition; Visual Materials; and Lake Angelus Observatory.
The Stanford R. Ovshinsky papers comprise materials documenting his long scientific career. Though the collection includes some information about his personal life, the files primarily provide insight into Ovshinsky's professional activities and involvement in the field of amorphous materials.
Subjects:
Alternative fuel vehicles.; Amorphous substances.; Electric vehicles--Batteries.; Energy Conversion Devices, Inc.; EV1 automobile--Research.; Inventors--Michigan.; Inventors--United States.; Nickel-metal hydride batteries--Research.; Ovshinsky, Stanford R.; Phase change memory--Research.; Prius automobile--Research.; Scientists--Michigan.; Scientists--United States.; Solar energy--Research.
Genre Terms:
CDs.; Color negatives.; Digital file formats.; Photographs.; Video recordings.; Videocassettes.
- Personal
  The Personal series (2.2 linear feet, 1 oversize box, and digital files; 1922-2012) contains information about Stanford Ovshinsky's life outside of work. This includes a wide variety of documents, beginning with his birth certificate, high school materials, and photographs from his childhood and marriage to his first wife Norma. A copy of Ovshinsky's FBI file, which he requested through the Freedom of Information and Privacy Act (FOIPA), is also available in this section, along with documents and correspondence demonstrating his political leanings and involvement. Family communication and financial records, a love letter from Iris Ovshinsky and the couple's marriage certificate, a book of remembrances from Ovshinsky's 80th birthday, his early efforts at poetry, selected excerpts from works about Ovshinsky's life, and his autobiographical drafts also appear in this series.
  - 70th birthday, VHS videocassette (Box 95)
  - 80th birthday remembrance book excerpts, 2002 (Box 1)
  - 80th birthday reminiscences, appreciations, and photographs, 2002; .ZIP file
  - Autobiography and political essays, 1990-1992; .ZIP file
  - Autobiography, 1992-1997 (Box 1)
  - Autobiography, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Autobiography notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Certificates -- birth and marriage, 1922; 1962 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Early poems, undated (Box 1)
  - Education
    - Buchtel High School -- class of '41, 1939-2001 (Box 1)
    - University of Akron, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Family tree, undated (Box 1)
  - Favored cartoons and quotes, undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mementos
    - 1970s (Box 1)
    - 1980s (Box 1)
  - Finances
    - Iris Ovshinsky's estate, 2009 (Box 1)
    - Real estate appraisal, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Revocable trust
      - Agreement, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
      - Demand notices, 2008-2012 (Box 1)
      - Promissory note, 2011 (Box 1)
  - Family correspondence
    - Dibner, Rob and Lora, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Dibner, Steven, 1999-2012 (Box 1)
    - Goddard, Angela, 2007 (Box 1)
    - Harper, Dani, 2011-2012 (Box 1)
    - Murphy, Natasha and Dave, 2007-2011 (Box 1)
    - Ovshinsky, Ben (Box 2)
      - 2010 (Box 2)
      - 2011-2012 (Box 2)
    - Ovshinsky, Dale, 2007-2012 (Box 2)
    - Ovshinsky, Harvey, 2010-2012 (Box 2)
  - Iris Ovshinsky
    - Boston University, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Death, August 2006 (Box 2)
    - Identification card-University of Michigan, 1947-1948 (Box 2)
    - Video memorial tribute, 2006; video
    - Resume and travel list, 1960-1978 (Box 2)
    - Vacation in Canada with Stan Ovshinsky, October 7, 1991; VHS videocassette (Box 88)
  - Miscellaneous, 1944-2004; 2 folders (Box 2)
    (resumes -- Robin Dibner and SRO, personal letters, neuro research & correspondence, gardening information)
  - Miscellaneous, May-July 2009 (Box 2)
    (medical exam, notes, family history -- Lithuania, photo of Stan and Rosa Ovshinsky)
  - Photographs of Ovshinsky family, 1937-1955(?) (Box 2)
  - Political
    - Bergman, Walter
      - 1962 (Box 2)
      - 1962-1981 (Box 2)
      - Ovshinsky speaking at Bergman's memorial service, October 9, 1999; Betacam SP videocassette (Box 94)
      - Bergman memorabilia album (Box 109)
        (letters from numerous activists and dignitaries, photographs and articles to 1962 dinner programs, 1962, 1963, and 1982 memorial service program, 1999)
      - Testimonial dinner commemorative binder, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Congress on Racial Equality (CORE), 1959-1961 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1966 (Box 2)
    - Dissent, 1956-1963 (Box 2)
      (correspondence, publications, and a love letter from Iris Ovshinsky)
    - FBI file
      - Central Industrial Personnel Security Board, 1953-1970 (Box 2)
      - Michigan State Police complaints, 1961-1969 (Box 2)
      - Ovshinsky miscellaneous information, 1953-1985 (Box 2)
      - Ovshinsky, Stanford, 1982 (Box 2)
      - SRO file released under FOIPA, 1969-1983 (Box 2)
    - Involvement, 1944-1965 (Box 2)
    - Politics notes and writings, 1964-1968 (Box 2)
    - Socialist membership cards, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
    - Thoughts on underdeveloped countries, 1960-1964 (Box 2)
    - Workmen's Circle -- Detroit, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Workmen's Circle, 4 Sony DVCAM videocassettes (Box 94)
- Correspondence, 1954-2012
  The Correspondence series (22 linear feet and digital files; 1954-2012) is divided into two subseries: Companies and Individuals. The majority of this series contains letters and emails that relate to business dealings or scientific topics.
  - Companies, 1965-2012
    The Companies subseries documents Ovshinsky's collaboration and involvement with a variety of corporations, institutions, and community organizations.
    - A-B, 1988-2012 bulk dates 2003-2011, 30 folders (Box 3)
    - Automation Alley video, 2008; video
    - C-Ch, 2003-2011 bulk dates 2007-2011, 20 folders (Box 4)
      (Photos: Chile-Stan and Iris Ovshinsky)
    - Cix-En. 1965-2012 bulk dates 2005-2007, 35 folders (Box 5)
      (Photos: ECD travel postcards)
    - Electric Battery Bicycle Company report, 2007; PDF
    - En-G, 1981-2012 bulk dates 2002-2008, 29 folders (Box 6)
      (Photographs: Euro Med. CD-R: First Energy Presentation Jan 26, 2007.)
    - H-In, 1997-2012 bulk dates 2006-2010, 23 folders (Box 7)
    - In-Misc., 1988-2012 bulk dates 2005-2008, 38 folders (Box 8)
    - Misc.-Oh, 1985-2011 bulk dates 2005-2008, 24 folders (Box 9)
      (Nasdaq-Stan and Iris Ovshinsky; Oakland University-Stan Ovshinsky)
    - "Walter Bergman, Freedom Rider", video
    - Ol-Se, 1988-2012 bulk dates 1995-2011, 25 folders (Box 10)
    - Sh-T, 1991-2012 bulk dates 2004-2007, 19 folders (Box 11)
    - U-Wa, 1955-2012 bulk dates 1999-2012, 24 folders (Box 12)
    - Workmen's Circle, 2000-2012; 8 folders (Box 13)
  - Individuals, 1954-2012
    The Individuals subseries contains correspondence from professors, scientists, friends, employees, consultants, and admirers. There are a number of letters from politicians in this subseries as well, such as Amalia Solórzano de Cárdenas, former First Lady of Mexico, Carl Levin, a long-serving United States Senator from Michigan, and Mark Schauer, a former United States Representative from the Detroit area and subsequently a Michigan gubernatorial candidate. The subseries also includes materials Ovshinsky gathered for his biographer Lillian Hoddeson, professor emerita of history at the University of Illinois and historian of Fermilab.
    - A-Bray, 1986-2012 bulk dates 2000-2012, 16 folders (Box 13)
    - Brockman-C, 1960-2011 bulk dates 2000-2010, 22 folders (Box 14)
      (Photograph: Cardenas, Lazaro and Amalia -- Lazaro former President of Mexico)
    - D-F, 1963-2012 bulk dates 2005-2012, 34 folders (Box 15)
      (Photographs: Del Bosque, Homero; Dang, Vijay-Ovshinsky's 90th birthday; Dhar, Subhash. CD: Ellison, Tom)
    - G-Hoddeson, 32 folders (Box 16)
      (Photographs: Garlovsky, David -- Stan and Iris Ovshinsky; Gasiorowski, Paul -- thick film deposits. CD: Gibson, Peter -- BSO carb zts folder; Heckeroth, Steve-PowerPoint Uni-Solar and sc roofing; Photographs: Hoddeson, Lillian -- biography materials 3. CD: Hoddeson, Lillian-biography materials 3 -- Ovonic Quantum Control Device media briefing)
    - Hoffer-I, 1954-2012 bulk dates 2002-2012, 19 folders (Box 17)
      (Howard, George -- Book appendix, SRO files)
    - J-K, 1972-2012 bulk dates 2001-2012, 26 folders (Box 18)
      (Photographs: Kane, Gordon-Stan Ovshinsky; Kolobov, Alex --Stan Ovshinsky; Kumar, Arun-Stan Ovshinsky)
    - L-Mi, 1955-2012 bulk dates 2000-2012, 30 folders (Box 19)
      (Photographs: Levin, Carl.)
    - Mi-Ovshinsky, 1960-2012(27 folders) (Box 20)
      (Photographs: Mitchell, Tom & Roseanne -- Stan Ovshinsky; Mott, Nevill P. -- statue of Mott; Ohta, Takeo-Stan Ovshinsky)
    - Ovshinsky-Pi, 1983-2012; 17 folders (Box 21)
    - Popescu-Slangerup, 1969-2012 bulk dates 2003-2010, 31 folders (Box 22)
      (Photographs: Shaiken, Harley 2000-2008, Shi, Luping-Stan Ovshinsky)
    - Smaga-T, 1983-2012 bulk dates 2003-2011, 26 folders (Box 23)
      (Photograph: Stempel, Robert 1 -- Stan Ovshinsky; Thiessen, Klaus-Stan Ovshinsky. CD: Takagi, Yasuo -- photographs and PowerPoint; Tamaka, Veiji -- photograph with Stan Ovshinsky.)
    - Sm-Za (supplemental), 1986-2000 bulk dates 1996-2000, 4 folders (Box 107)
    - V-Z, 1992-2012; 27 folders (Box 24)
      (Photographs: Winkelman, Margaret -- Stan Ovshinsky; Zeisel, Eva)
- Research and Subject Files, 1955-2010
  The Research and Subject Files series (5.2 linear feet; 1955-2010) contains documents from Ovshinsky's research and collaboration with other scientists on a variety of technical subjects. Research notes, correspondence, and academic papers constitute the majority of the documents found in this series. These files highlight the wide range of Ovshinsky's interests, with topics ranging from the brain and neurophysiology to optical memory. While research files exist throughout the collection, this series holds documents that, for the most part, are not directly connected to one of his many businesses. Of the subject areas in the series, files pertaining to cosmology and superconductivity have the largest number of documents and contain substantial amounts of collaborative correspondence between Ovshinsky, Morrel Cohen, and Hellmut Fritzsche.
  - Filing Index, undated (Box 25)
  - Aeroviroment, July 1981 (Box 25)
  - Angstrom, undated (Box 25)
  - Blood, 1955-1963(?), 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Brain, 1955-1996; 4 folders (Box 25)
  - Catalysts, 1979-1980 (Box 25)
  - Cerebellum, ca. 1955 (Box 25)
  - Chemical Bonding, undated; 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Chemical Modification, 1977-1981 (Box 25)
  - Cognitive Computer, 1955-2010; 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Cosmology, 1985-2007; 11 folders (Box 25)
  - Cosmology, 1985-2007; 11 folders (Box 26)
  - Encryption, 1996-2000 (Box 26)
  - Fluorine, 1978 (Box 26)
  - Fuel cells, 1979 (Box 26)
  - Fusion, 1989 (Box 26)
  - Greenhouse Gasses, 1989-1997 (Box 26)
  - Hydrogen, 1979; 1997; 2003; 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Imaging, 1970 (Box 26)
  - Intelligence, 1950-1962; 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Introns (Box 27)
  - Magnetic particle control (Box 27)
  - Memristors, undated (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous, 1971-1979 (Box 27)
  - Neurophysiology, 1955-1965; 7 folders (Box 27)
  - Optical Memory, 1977-2001 (Box 27)
  - Photovoltaic, 1980-2008; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Physical Theory, 1965-1968 (Box 27)
  - Semiconductors, 1955-1968; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Sony chairman Morita interview, April 1990; VHS videocassette (Box 103)
  - Superconductivity, 1975-1994; 15 folders (Box 28)
  - Superconductivity, 1965-1995; 31 folders (Box 29)
  - Superconductivity, 1977-1990; 26 folders (Box 29)
  - "Superconductors," Channel 2 (name of channel not specified), July 21, 1987; VHS videocassette (Box 29)
  - Switching, 1959-1970; 9 folders (Box 61)
  - Thermoelectricity, 1960s-1970s (Box 61)
  - Vision, 1998 (Box 61)
- Publications
  The Publications series (13.4 linear feet and 3 oversize volumes; 1955-2012) includes both scientific and popular printed works. Technical papers written by Ovshinsky and ECD employees or directors comprise a significant portion of the series; these works, which primarily derive from the period between 1968 and 1995, document the research interests of Ovshinsky and other scientists with whom he worked in his heyday. On occasion, original drafts, collaborative correspondence, and handwritten research notes accompany the articles. Materials produced by business magazines, Detroit-area newspapers, and other accessible publishers help to contextualize the technical developments and situate them in the vocabulary of the lay reader.
  - Technical Publications -- Ovshinsky and ECD
    - --, 1955; 1970; 83 folders (Box 30)
    - --, 1971; 1975; 61 folders (Box 31)
    - --, 1976; 1981; 70 folders (Box 32)
    - supplemental publications, 1975-1980; 9 folders (Box 107)
    - --, 1982; 1984; 81 folders (Box 33)
    - --, 1985; 1986; 75 folders (Box 34)
    - --, 1987; 1993; 80 folders (Box 35)
    - --, 1994; 2000; 68 folders (Box 36)
    - --, 2001; 2012; 42 folders (Box 37)
  - Newspapers, Magazines, and Books, 1963-2012
    - 1966-2012 (Box 37)
    - Akron Beacon Journal, 2005-ECD, 1963-1967; 50 folders (Box 38)
    - ECD, 1967-1977; 23 folders (Box 39)
    - ECD, 1978-2002-H, 30 folders (Box 40)
    - I-Optical Memory News, 48 folders (Box 41)
    - Ovonic Link -- Z, 38 folders (Box 42)
    - Newspaper clippings scrapbook, 1963; 1966 (Volume 1)
    - Newspaper clippings scrapbook, 1963; 1968 (Volume 2)
    - Newspaper clippings scrapbook, (with gaps), 1969-1996 (Volume 3)
- Business Administration, 1943-2009
  The Business Administration series (26.9 linear feet, 4 oversize boxes, and digital files; 1943-2012) contains materials that extensively document Stanford Ovshinsky's commercial ventures. This series is divided into four subseries based on Ovshinsky's early career, his work with Energy Conversion Devices, and activities of the Institute for Amorphous Studies. Product literature espousing the benefits of new developments, business and technical materials documenting the evolution of these products, and shareholder reports comprise a significant portion of the series. Prominently represented as well are meeting minutes from the Board of Directors of the Institute for Amorphous Studies (IAS), advertisements and information about the IAS lecture series, and materials regarding Ovshinsky's participation in symposia around the world and festschrifts honoring David Adler, Hellmut Fritzsche, Nevill Mott, and Heinz Henisch. Internal correspondence, discussions of employee discontent, and audits also appear in the Business Administration series.
  - General, 1952-2007
    - Audit and internal investigations, 1993-2005 (Box 43)
    - Automation Alley, 2007 (Box 43)
    - Business cards-Stan Ovshinsky, undated (Box 43)
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1952-1962 (Box 43)
    - Early business
      - Amgears, Hupp Corp., General Automation, and personal correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 43)
      - Ovitron, Stanford Roberts, New Britain, Hupp-Servo steer, magnet ball controls, switches and relays, 1949-1959 (Box 43)
      - Tann Corporation agreements, press releases, promotional literature, proofs of concepts, scientific schematics, Stan and Herbert Ovshinsky patent applications and related correspondence, 1955-1959; 2 folders (Box 107)
    - Early neuroscience research, 1957 (?) (Box 43)
    - History, 1962-1983; 2 folders (Box 43)
      (Folder 1 contains photographs)
    - Hupp Corporation